Guide to the African American Studies Records
University of Houston Libraries.
African American Studies Records
1990-2001
2001-005
University of Houston. African American Studies Program
8.50 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The collection includes information about the history of the African American Studies Program, the First Annual Wilson Whitley Golf Tournament, fellowship programs, and study abroad programs. Materials in the collection include annual reports, brochures, catalogs, development plans, grant proposals, and reports to the community.
Historical Note:
In response to student demands, the African American Studies Program was established during the late 1960s. The program offers courses that focus on the history and culture of African Americans and the contributions that people of African descent have made to American and world civilizations.
Over the past thirty years the African American Studies Program has added new courses, received additional and continuous funding, stimulated increased student interest, and expanded its associated cultural activities and community presence. Recruitment and retention of African American students has also been an important goal of the African American Studies Program. Enrollment now (as of 2002) stands at over 1,600 students.
The organization outlined its goals for the nineties as: (1) creating a new generation of leaders who challenge stereotypes, prejudice, discrimination and belief systems that hinder the intellectual emancipation and personal growth of all members of society, (2) promoting a mutual understanding between various ethnic and cultural groups of the university, and (3) developing an awareness of the richness of the African American experience and the contributions of African Americans to society.
References:
African American Studies Program Handout, Box 2, folder 1.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston; University of Houston. African American Studies Program.
Genre/Form of Material:
Annual reports; Brochures; Catalogs (documents); Reports; Souvenirs
Personal Name:
Eusan, Lynn Cecilia; Whitley, Wilson
Acquisition Information:
Transferred by African American Studies Program, 2001. Addition materials arrived in 2016 as accession #2016-014.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Scope and Contents
The processed collection consists of 2.5 linear feet of materials. These materials arrived at the archives in relatively good order, which has been maintained where possible. The collection includes information about the history of the African American Studies Program, the First Annual Wilson Whitley Golf Tournament, fellowship programs, and study abroad programs. Materials in the collection include annual reports, brochures, catalogs, development plans, grant proposals, and reports to the community. This collection is divided into four series: Administrative Records, Wilson Whitley Memorial Celebrity Golf Tournament, Scholarships, Fellowships and Awards; and Study Abroad Programs. The collection covers the years from 1990 to 2001 with one item, a Tribute to Lynn Eusan, from 1971.
An additional 6 linear feet of material has since been added to the collection, but is not yet fully processed. Please contact the curator with questions about access to these materials.
Detailed List of Contents
- Administrative Records, 1990-2001
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged alphabetically, this series contains forty-six folders dating from 1990 to 2001. Overall, the original folder order has been maintained. This series contains a wide range of materials relating to the administration of the African American Studies program. Materials include annual reports, development plans, reports to the community, grant proposals, newsletters, and publications. This series also contains grievance procedures and policy guidelines for the program.
  - Activities Summary, Spring 1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Activities Summary, Fall 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 4a)
  - Annual Report, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 4b)
  - Atlas Travel Inc., 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Black Exchange, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Books, African American Studies, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brochure Revisions, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Budget Line Item, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Catalogs, Miscellaneous, 1993-2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Catalogs, Film and Video, 1993-1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Center for the Study of African American Culture, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Conference, First Annual African Holocaust, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Conference, National (Letters sent), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Development Plan, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Development Plan, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dinner President, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fundraising, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Graduation Reception, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Grant Proposal, National Endowment for the Humanities, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Grievance Procedures/Policy, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Haley, D. Chairperson of the French Committee, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Harris, Bernard, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Humanities, Fine Arts and Communications, College of, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Institute for African American Policy Research, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Karenga, Dr. Maulana, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Logo, Camera Ready, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Minority Male Initiative, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Minors' Association, 1993-1997 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Newsletter, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Program Informational/History, 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Programs, Various Institutions, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Recruitment, Biology, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Recruitment, Minority, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Report to the Community, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Retention Focus Group, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Special Projects, May 1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Speakers, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Student Publications, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Teen Forum, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Twenty-fifth Anniversary, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Urban Experience Program, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Video Inventory, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Walk-A-thon, Friends Committee, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Women's History Panel, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Wilson Whitley Memorial Celebrity Golf Tournament, 1992-1994
  This series contains a wide range of materials relating to the First Annual Wilson Whitley Golf Tournament. Materials in this series consist of correspondence, press releases, mailing lists, and meeting minutes related to the event. The series contains twenty-four folders dating from 1992-1994 and arranged alphabetically. The tournament was named after Wilson Whitley the late University of Houston All-American football player. In 1976, Whitley was voted the Best Defensive Lineman in college football. He later played professionally with the Cincinnati Bengals for many seasons. After retirement from the National Football League, Whitley worked as an executive for Holiday Inn Worldwide. At the time of his death, he was working on a celebrity golf tournament to benefit the Scholarship Fund of the African American Studies Program. In its first year, the tournament generated over $40,000 in gross revenues. Some of the celebrity players included, Robert Newhouse, Alois Blackwell, Butch Woolfolf, Curtis Duncan, Ross Browner, Isaac Curtis, Francis Page, Andre Ware, Carl Lewis, and Otis Birdsong.
  - Advertisement for Booklet, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Celebrity Confirmations First Annual, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Celebrity Confirmations, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Celebrity Correspondence, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Conference Letters-Golfers and Celebrities, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Confirmation Letters, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Corporate Responses, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Corporate Sponsor Confirmation, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Friends Committee-Gold Tournament, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Golf Tournament, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Golf Tournament, Agenda and Minutes, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Golf Tournament Correspondence to Corporations, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Golf Tournament-Executive Committee, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Golf Tournament Income/Expenses, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Mailing List for Golf Tournament, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Mailing List-Players, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Press Release, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Registered Players for Tournament, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Souvenir Booklet, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Things to do List Golf Tournament, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Tournament Mailing, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Tournament wrap-up Meeting, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Wilson Whitley, Memorial, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Wilson Whitley Tournament Work Assignments, Members, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Scholarships, Fellowships and Awards, 1995-1996
  This series contains seven folders related to various scholarships, fellowships, and awards or tributes to prominent members of the African American community. Materials include applications, scholarship requirements, letters of congratulations to award winners, and a small amount of correspondence. Most of the materials date from the 1995-1996 academic school year. Transcripts have been removed and destroyed, following the Texas Open Records Act. Some of the different awards include: the Sheeler Scholarship Fund, the Academic Excellence Scholarship, the African American Studies Graduate Fellowship Program, the African American Studies Program, Debbie Haley Community Service Scholarship, and the John Ruben Sheeler Memorial Scholarship Awards.
  - Graduate Fellowship Application, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Graduate Fellowship Program, Application Materials, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Debbie Haley Adult Community Service Award, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Barbara Jordan, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Nia Becnel Memorial, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - John Ruben Sheeler Memorial Scholarship Award, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Tribute to Lynn Eusan, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Study Abroad Programs, 1996-1999
  This series consists of fifteen folders, which contain informational materials relating to different study abroad programs including locations in Ghana, South Africa, Tunisia, England, Spain, Zimbabwe, France, India, Israel, and Jamaica. Most of the materials in these folders date between 1996-1999 and are arranged alphabetically.
  - Council Study Abroad, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Crossroads Africa, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Education Abroad, College Consortium for International Studies, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Education Abroad Programs, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - International Education Fee Scholarship, Study Abroad, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Intercultural Communication Class, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - International Partnership for Service Learning, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - International Students, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Nyanza Project, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Syracuse Study Abroad, 1996-1998 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Tanzania Program-Washington University, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Teaching Abroad, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Trinidad, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Uongozi Institute, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Wisconsin Study Abroad, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Unprocessed accessions
  2 linear feet of unprocessed materials accompany the main collection. An additional 4 linear feet arrived in 2016 as accession #2016-014.